Welcome, and
welcome to people that are now watching us.
We are talking about the Financial Markets International
Money Transfer Amendment Bill, which is a member's bill in the name
of Arena Williams, and she is now at the table, and we have 15
minutes with you. That's inclusive of question time, so I will hand
to you.
Thank you, Madam Chair. I will leave plenty of time for questions.
But colleagues,
this is a funny setup, and I thought I would take just a minute to tell you why
I've asked governance and administration to take this on as a piece of work,
why we find ourselves here with a member's
bill to deal with an issue which MBIE has provided advice on to four
successive commerce ministers, beginning with the Honorable Dr.
David Clark,
followed by the Honorable Duncan Webb, the Honorable Scott Simpson,
and now the current commerce minister.
And then finally, I'll leave you with some remarks about why
this issue is a real-world issue. It is one that began with a
constituent case for me in 2023,
and will remain something which affects all of us, not
only as electorate MPs, but as representatives and advocates for the diverse
communities within New Zealand who use these services, and the vulnerable
consumers who are disproportionately affected by these high costs
that New Zealanders pay. So to begin,
why do we find ourselves here? Because the regime that manages
international money transfers and their costs in some jurisdictions has a natural
home, a natural regulator, but because we find ourselves with a sort of Twin
Peaks regulation system, where we have a
banking regulator, financial services from the financial markets,
we also have MBIE looking across these sorts of products,
and primarily concerned with this sort of product because it is something that
consumers should be able to see the ticket price and pay the ticket price.
And then we also have international arrangements,
where it is important that we get our settings right in New
Zealand so that consumers who are making these transfers in New
Zealand, say to a bank account in the Pacific, have
transparency, and so that other jurisdictions that
work with us and are the main recipients or the main
contributors are getting a fair deal.
So there's no one regulator who's responsible for this issue.
I think this is an issue where we need greater transparency
so that the rules are fair for everyone, and that's why I've asked you to take a
look under the hood. It doesn't necessarily sit with EPC, it doesn't necessarily
sit with EDZ.
This is something which affects every New Zealander at least a few
times a year, but for some people every week when they are sending their
wages overseas to family members.
So why is this something which successive governments have had a crack at
and haven't been able to land? And this is a matter of public record,
your question about, is there a problem?
Yes, successive commerce ministers have thought this is a problem.
It's not only National ministers who have been asked
to have a look at this, it's also Labor ministers, but it is something that has
sort of fallen through the cracks of who is responsible for it.
The total size of the transfer market in New Zealand at
the end of this decade will be close to a billion dollars just in
the fees that we pay. About half of those are small business
and business fees, and then the other half includes a good whack
of consumer fees, around $200 million off the top of my
head, that ordinary people like you and me are paying on top of what
we would be paying if we were in a more competitive market like the UK or like the
EU. So that is a net drag on not only New Zealand's
productivity, but also on the price that consumers pay that's not going back into
their mortgages, it's not going back into their car loans, it's not going back into
those things that help them with the cost of living and make sure
that they can pay their bills at the end of the week.
Who does this primarily affect? Well,
you might imagine that we're talking here about workers who are making
payments every week and every fortnight. That is true.
The majority of these people who are hit by these larger fees
are also people with either English as a second language barriers, or people who
see transfer companies in the street,
who are advertising to them that there is a zero fee or
0% fee. And so in New Zealand, they are not entitled to
rely on that claim. But though they are being advertised a 0%
fee, those people who are paying their wages every week are actually paying quite a
large fee, and by the end of the year, they might be paying $2,000 to
$4,000 for a minimum wage worker
in that 0% fee.
But we're also talking about people who are booking holidays, booking
experiences, booking things in New Zealand currency where they're
going on a trip or a holiday. We're also talking about people who are migrating.
A
woman in my last public meeting about this told me that in her move from the
Philippines to New Zealand, she was caught in this and lost more than
$10,000, which she felt like she just didn't want to quite pass out
through about how much money that was for her when she was
making the biggest transfer she will ever make, the biggest investment to move
to a new country, to open a new business here,
because she felt like it was such a big investment and a
pretty humiliating one for her. We're also talking about people who
are older. Older New Zealanders are
more likely to be using these services and not alternatives,
which
offer a more competitive rate, because the most competitive
options in the New Zealand market right now are New Zealand startups.
They're New Zealand tech entrepreneurs who are seeing an opportunity right here
because the margin is so big that if you are a young New
Zealand tech hopeful, you can build a business that competes with
the banks, that competes with those transfer companies in the street,
and even if you've invested a few thousand dollars of your own money, you can make
something and with not a big company And not a big
customer base, you can actually make some money because the opportunity there
is so large because these margins have not been competed
down over time. This is a clear use of market power
where the largest incumbents have used their market size to
keep those big margins high.
This is something where I'm sure that my colleagues who have been briefed
on this before by officials would be frustrated by the briefing
that the committee has received, because that is the information that ministers
have received the last 10 years, but this still remains a problem.
And it remains a problem because those margins remain high.
There's not a clear regulating, and the rules that I have
proposed in my member's bill put the regulation-making power with the
regulator, with me. I have not proposed that this committee should
come up with a definition of what is a fair margin.
I have not suggested to you a cap. I have not suggested to you a regime which
requires the sorts of information that will be displayed.
I have simply suggested to you that you should give a regulation-making power
to the regulators, because that is the appropriate role for this parliament, and
that they should come up with the rules which are clear, and so everyone has a fair
playing field. My suggestion would be that the rules should make
everyone use the same sorts of disclosure that the apps have to use
already. Because we are seeing a growth in that market for New Zealanders, that
more and more people are switching to financial
apps and online services that are either New Zealand-based startups or
that are international competitors with our banks.
And that the fact that they can do it says to me that everyone
should be doing it, and that everybody in New Zealand should be able to get
the same fair deal that the people who are tech-savvy,
they're diligent, they're watching their money, they're well-informed,
wealthy people, are able to access by
using those services. I just want that for everyone.
So happy to take questions about the-
Okay, thank you. We've about six minutes for questions.
So Melissa, I'll start with you.
Thank you. Thank you for your submission.
Two questions in related to the example that you gave.
One is actually regarding the Filipino who was actually-
Yes
... migrating. You were talking about losing $10,000.
Yes.
So, what
is that fee for, and where did that fee go to?
Yeah.
Is one question. The other one is, you talked about when people are transferring
money,
the charge, they're actually paying a fee of $1,000.
Yeah.
So similar question.
What is the charge?
Where is the charge?
Yeah.
Who's actually taking it, and what percentage is it?
Great points. Okay. So, in this particular example, we
can work it through. There are four transactions that this woman made,
and they had to be at different times because of different points at which she was
able to sell her assets. She sold a couple of properties, and she also sold her
business, and she was then buying in New Zealand a mix of assets and
money in a bank account. So each transfer
for her had a slightly different rate, and two of them had a fee.
Was it through a bank?
Two were through a bank, and one was through a service.
And-
What service?
One of the services that she used was an app for her cash, and
that had a very low fee, and that fee was disclosed to her.
Was it Wise or PayPal or something else?
Not sure. I think it was one of the bigger ones, like I think it might've been
Zoom.
But not quite sure. She didn't tell me, but she-
Right
... it's also quite hard to get that specific information out of people because
they don't want to pass it out. But she did use one service, which was a low fee.
Then she used another service
once she was basically
at the point of buying a business,
and that
also,
the point of that was that there was a big fee attached to that one that
was also visible to her, but a large fee that she couldn't get out
of, which ended up being about $2,000, just the fee.
So it was added on to the transaction-
Added on to the transaction
... or is she taken out from her money?
Added on to the transaction.
Right.
The two next ones,
those were the ones with the foreign effects spread, where it was a
product which was advertised to her as a 0% fee,
but in the foreign exchange spread,
the RBNZ rate for the New Zealand dollar would be set
here, a transfer rate was set
here.
So within that, there was a margin that her transfer company was
making that was not disclosed to her first.
They would've been advertising that the New Zealand dollar was here,
when really New Zealand dollars were available to consumers like her at this
price. And that's the margin which this bill seeks to
regulate. It doesn't seek to regulate the two first kinds of fees,
because those were disclosed to her.
But in the second two transactions, which added
up to be fees of about $6,500 for
her, those are the fees that this bill's seeking to sort out.
And I'm not trying to sort it out for
our entire banking relationships, say, around the Asia-Pacific.
I'm just trying to sort it out here in New Zealand, because New
Zealand-based Filipinos who are making those
transactions to the Philippines are paying more
in the New Zealand market. The margins are huge in the New Zealand
market, because we haven't had any degree of
competition around those sorts of
transfer services. We're just getting to the stage.
And to invite more of that competition, we have to give them an even playing
field, or else
that competition that we're enjoying now where we're seeing new entrants coming
into the market, they will also be able to charge higher and higher
prices. We have to get our regulatory settings right so everyone comes down to a
competitive price.
Okay, thank you. Tim.
Yeah, just can I just ask two questions?
So you-
You kind of addressed it, but not really. Sorry, there's two parts to it.
So, one is
why it's at GNA. And I understand you said, well, that's not quite FSE,
it's not quite economic development, but it's definitely not GNA, right?
Because the FMA never reports here, MBIE never reports here.
We never deal with these kind of issues. So why has it come here?
I'm really passionate about sorting this out as a broader issue
for our relationships within the Pacific corridors, within, and
comparing ourselves to jurisdictions that we like to compare ourselves to, like
Australia, like the UK. We should have a regime which is most
similar to the governance arrangements within those countries.
We cannot reorganize the regulators to have a
stronger look at the sorts of prices that we put on financial products,
but we can make sure that we've got the right responsibility at this level.
That's why the regulation-making power,
I also considered sending it to the committee, which is the
expert committee for regulations, the Relations Review Committee,
because all I'm asking for is a new regulation-making power.
So in terms of the legislative design of this, nothing is subject matter
expert. Everything is the way that Parliament would delegate to a regulator.
But
I still don't hear why GNA. I get there's a
Pacific bit, maybe that's foreign affairs, I don't know.
There's a regulation-
Could be foreign affairs, could be regs, yeah
... but I haven't heard anything that, like it's not
DIA, it's not NEMA, it's not
local government, it's not any of the places that this committee deals
with. I'm just
trying to understand why-
You're right. There are several committees that this could have-
We need to move on because we haven't got much time, so-
Okay. So the other part was, can you just tell us why previous ministers
from whatever party, Duncan, whomever, why weren't they able to do
this?
It's something which has come up in, say, the COFI
regime, which is about consumer care and the expectations we have on
banks, financial institutions.
It's in the weeds of the regulation-making
powers, and yet we still don't have a regulation that is specific
around this.
So,
they could have done it, just didn't hit the priority level
I think if we were having this discussion in 2019 and in
2022 when the lid was off COFI,
you might have also received advice, and ministers certainly did,
that we would have seen a tapering off of this in
New Zealand's market because the rules also
require fair dealing, pricing transparency of other sorts of
products,
that the powers already exist, and
that we would have seen market practice evolve
to...
It's in the shades of gray, and governments have
gone darker and darker gray in the specificity around this.
But this is the first time we've considered a specific requirement on
the regulator to implement rules around this.
Didn't you say it went to David Clark?
We're not going to get there now, sorry, because-
Okay
... we've run out of time, and I'm sorry about that.
We do have some other questions, but maybe members can actually get those to you
directly in that-
Yep
... article.
Cool. Thank you.
So we're actually opening now for submissions, and the first submission was the
Peanut Butter Collective, please. Hello, Paul.
Hello.
And,
I'm going to hand over, but Paul, I haven't seen you for a long time, so
it's wonderful to see you.
Yeah. Thank you, Jane, Madam Chair, and members of the committee.
And I'm going to move, Jane.
I did have the pleasure of visiting Jane at a school many years ago-
Yes, yeah
... when I was a public servant, and haven't had much to do with her since, but-
I know
... to follow you on the news.
And unfortunately, I have to leave now, but-
Okay
... yeah. But it's lovely to see you. Yeah.
I also have a good friend from the Philippines.
She lives here in New Zealand and regularly sends money back to support her
parents. She has a business degree.
She works in the finance industry here in New Zealand.
She shops around for a good rate, and yet she was
surprised by the evidence my research turned up and what she's
paying in margins
within the exchange rate component not easily visible for her.
I guess I see that if somebody as capable as
she can't make the right decisions with that background, then
it's not a failure of the consumer or of the shopper, but there's
something else that's broken here in the system.
I'm Paul Seiler, I'm the co-founder of the Peanut Butter Collective.
We're a pre-revenue startup looking to apply data
method transparency of ruthless honesty to help Kiwi households get better
deals on life's essentials.
This bill came up in an environmental scan for me of what's happening.
There's a high mission overlap and zero business plan
overlap. So we're here based on evidence and method, nothing to do
with self-gain, nor lived harm, actually.
I personally don't send much money anywhere else.
To us, the problem is one that the fee
paid to remit money has two components. One is visible up front.
It might be zero, or it might be a number different.
The other is hidden within the exchange rate margin.
This is often not visible at the point of making a transaction and makes
comparison very difficult.
On the New Zealand Tonga corridor,
the World Bank data shows that the average rate for the fee
is around about 8%, including both components, but the range is what's
interesting. From about 17% for the main banks, with quite a low
spread around that number, down to 3% for the newer
fintech-like products.
The difference was quite alarming to me and kind of reinforces what the Commerce
Commission found, that the pricing is opaque and poorly understood.
So Peanut Butter Collective supports the bill, and we ask for a number of
changes. Only two I'll speak to here.
The first is that the binding minimum includes the fee that is
disclosed and the margin within the exchange rate, that those two are
locked together and made transparent so shoppers can make informed choices.
The second, we believe that the duty-
Should follow the activity of sending money so that it reaches all providers that
undertake this activity, not limited to only banks, insurers, or deposit
takers who might be the natural place this would
fall in the way that it's currently written.
We see this as a small bill that could
make a real difference for competition and for families.
I'm happy to take your questions.
Yeah, Le Manea.
Thank you for your submission. It's really helpful to try and
understand issues. And I'm really concerned about hearing
what you've provided here in terms of consumers having a
very clear suite of options and then understanding you could either be
front-loaded or not. It's really helpful.
And this is a problem in our community, because I'm talking to people every week,
who send remittances back home because they have their own obligations, whether
it's Pacific or ethnic.
The question I wanted to ask was, in terms
of the
range of, so you've outlined in your example, there was a
front-load cost of 17%, but it's the range.
It's the range. So are you saying to the committee that,
in terms of the range, who actually decides the range, or is it
just so out there that it's up to each business to
charge that range without having to
inform the consumer?
Individual providers of the service choose their own
exchange rate. They have better information than most of their
customers in choosing that. I'm not seeking any regulation around
the exchange rate they choose. I believe that businesses should be able to make
that choice.
Sure.
But they should declare the divergence between a published
mid-rate
that all providers in the market use, certainly for the same channel,
and whatever rate they wish to charge.
That would get made visible upfront, in a standardized format,
so that shoppers, consumers can make a choice.
Just supplementary, Chair.
Please.
Just a supplementary on that. To declare that
even if English is a second language, because a lot of the people that I deal with,
you would actually go to a... Well, from what I can understand from local
examples, you would choose a provider or a
business that you've had really good feedback from
family or people in the community because there's that trusted
relationship.
So just in your point of declaration upfront,
that this is the cost. You're going to put in, for example,
$100, but there's these charges to be aware of.
So they've disclosed it right up front.
Mm-hmm.
So are you saying there's quite a mix in terms of businesses providing that
education for consumers?
There's no required disclosure. There's no standardized way of
conveying that, and providers act differently.
It would be difficult for any group of people,
any whanau or network, to make an informed decision, which others would
then follow based on trusted advice.
I'd just like the information to be transparent, comparable.
And then consumers, whether individual or larger groups, will make
informed decisions and
reward appropriate behaviors.
Thank you.
Andy Foster.
Yeah. Thank you very much, Paul. The question I wanted to ask is, these
organizations which are outside of COFI at the moment.
So I would've thought if you, there's a question, no, can't ask that.
A question I was interested in exploring was,
I would've thought it's an advantage from a, if I'm a consumer and
I see somebody who's being transparent about their fees,
I'd be more inclined to say I like that, as opposed to somebody who's opaque.
If the
organizations we're talking about remain opaque, then I would've
thought they would lose market share. People would tend to...
So I'm interested in your thoughts on that.
And secondly, you seem to be saying that the obligation attached, you
said the obligation attached to the activity providing an international money
transfer service, regardless of whether you're inside of COFI or not inside of
COFI. Now, I don't know, but you might give some advice on whether that would
require a sizable rearrangement of the COFI regime.
So, on the first question that you asked
about the reward for those who are
transparent or opaque.
Effectively, yes.
It's difficult to make fair comparisons when the numbers don't stack up.
The business might go to the organization who pitches zero fees, and that's a
true claim. There is a zero fee, so there's no breach of fair
trading in their other regulation.
It's just that the money that is recovered to run the cost of the service and any
margin that provider chooses is invisible at the point of making a
decision or beyond many people's point of comparison.
I don't have a view really on whether opacity should be,
maybe I do. Opacity shouldn't be allowed to continue just because people might get
rewarded for being transparent when we could easily
solve the issue of
transparent for all comparable easily. Okay?
So the second part of the question.
On the COFI regime?
Yeah, which is, effectively if you're requiring, and this'll be something to
probably ask the officials later on, but,
if you're essentially, the COFI regime covers a certain range of
organizations. Doesn't cover another lot.
What you're kind of suggesting is that this arrangement covers both, and that
I don't know what that does to the architecture of the COFI regime.
I'm not an expert on that. It was the best home I could find for an obligation
that could apply with the lightest touch.
It is important not to force too high compliance costs on
smaller and lower margin operators because the corridors to Pacific
Islands have always been very shallow for capital flows.
It would be a shame if good work done here to increase
transparency and comparability penalized or forced out of
existence, the very providers who are challenging the established
high rates in providing alternative flows for currency.
Okay. We've got one minute left for Dr Shane Rickardson.
Thank you. You're proposing a baseline comparator, a margin
comparator. Just describe that a bit more.
In other regimes that have tackled this well ahead of ourselves, so
European Union, Singapore, Canada, England, United
States, they set a mid-market exchange rate
against which all rates used for one service are measured.
Who's they?
That differs by jurisdiction. It could be a central
agency of government. Some people have borrowed from international published
rates because the sheer number of
currency-to-currency combinations is very high.
That market rate is known, it can be published daily, and I do accept that rates
change within the day and there's allowance made in the details for how you could
deviate from that. But it's not saying that's the rate you must use, it's saying
that is the rate against which your currency exchange rate is measured.
The difference, I'm not saying with margin, as in I'm saying it's a
fee and margin, but it's part of the
cost to the consumer for using the service, and that it should be
added to the fee in a visible, easy to
calculate way, and then I or others make their decision about which remittance
service do I use.
Thanks, Paul. We're out of time there. Appreciate your time today.
We're going to move online to Wise, and I think we've got Jack
Pincheski
joining us.
Good morning.
Good morning. We've got 10 minutes for you.
I'll let you know when there's a minute to run, but you might like to leave some
time for questions. It's all yours.
Absolutely, Chair. Thank you so much. My name's Jack Pincheski.
I'm the APAC Government Relations Lead for Wise.
We're a global technology company that's building the best way to move and send
money around the world. And I should just start by saying Wise was
established on the basis of our
CEO founder, Kristo Käärmann, being frustrated by his inability
to send money overseas without being hit with hidden FX fees.
And we describe hidden FX fees as the differential between the
mid-market rate or the rate you'd see on Google, and the rate that
you'd be charged by a high street bank.
We are a fast-growing company. We've got 19 million people and businesses using us
worldwide.
Our business is the movement of money across borders.
We operate in New Zealand. We've established our New Zealand entity.
We have many people in New Zealand who are our customers.
We have hundreds of thousands of New Zealanders who use us regularly to
send money to family overseas, or to receive money from overseas, or to make
spending decisions.
We are very excited about the prospect of this bill improving competition
for international payments in New Zealand.
We think that this bill will drive a large amount of competition in the
market by giving people the knowledge and the necessary
information that they need to make the best decision for themselves.
Currently, we see the regime for international money transfers as being opaque,
subject to no specific regulation, and it leads to poorer outcomes for particularly
small businesses who may be using the least
cost-effective way to send money or receive money from overseas.
This has been an issue which we've been advocating for in New Zealand for a number
of years. We were speaking to the Commerce Commission about this as far
back, I think, as 2022 and 2023. And in 2024, the New Zealand
Commerce Commission, I think you'd be aware, found that this is a very
effective area to improve competition for these
services. I'll
wind up by saying we endorse this bill.
We believe it will be a mechanism that will improve
competition, and I'd be very, very happy to talk to the mechanics of the
specifics, and provide you with some insight into what might be a better way
to proceed.
Thank you. Appreciate your time. I'm just looking to see if there's any
questions, and we'll start with Lamanga Olivia Susini.
Thanks. Thank you for your presentation.
I'm really interested with your comments that to
increase knowledge for consumers, because the current
settings in place don't encourage it, and there's quite some
confusion. So I do know with the Pacific corridors,
they will go with trusted providers, but
the knowledge of choosing a provider is quite
limited, and because English is limited as well for some of our
community.
Yes, absolutely. So the barriers to choosing the best
provider for a person, and obviously there's different reasons why someone might
choose an FX provider.
A person might choose an FX provider based on trust.
They know and trust their bank, or they know and trust the FX provider or
the international money transfer provider.
There is, though, a very large section of the population who would be motivated by
cost, and obviously, when we're talking about remittances and sending money
back home that's been hard-earned by a person to their family,
they're going to be highly motivated by cost.
The difficulty with the present situation is that a person sending money
is not aware of the full cost that would be
assessed to them
if they're not told the differential between a benchmark rate
and the FX rate, which is
charged to them by their bank or international money transfer provider.
And that piece of information, that element of price discovery,
is absolutely critical for a competitive market.
For a person to make that decision,
they need to have it illustrated to them, preferably in dollar terms, at the point
of transmission. So we believe this bill, if
our recommendations on improving this bill are taken, we believe that that
will- Ensure that consumers will be able to see exactly what it is that
they're paying at the point of transmission, which may prompt
consumer switching behavior, which is one of the key parts of trying to
make a consumer market more competitive.
It would be a consumer switching from one provider who they deem to be too
expensive to another provider that they deem to be more suitable for their needs.
Just a follow-up, Hugh?
Yes. Yeah.
Very quick.
Go on.
In terms of providers or businesses offering their services,
would this bill be able to achieve a better
system that would be clearer to New Zealand
consumers to be able to go shopping, because
I understand that rate is a little bit more, that rate is
better, that's more, I'd be happy to pay that.
Because my $100 that I'm sending to Samoa or wherever-
Mm
... turns into actually $80 or even $70 because of all
these charges?
Yeah, so there could be a few reasons for that.
The first could be that there are correspondent banking fees.
So correspondent banking fees could be the fee that's charged at the end of the
process.
But this would solve the issue of the hidden fee.
So correspondent banking fees, I believe they dealt with the issue of correspondent
banking fees in Australia by requiring the transmitting bank
to best disclose what the correspondent bank fee would be,
although that's a fee that's not charged by the sending bank, it's charged by the
receiving bank. But the more insidious part
of fees in international money transfer is the hidden fee.
This is the fee that you do not see in
any documentation about these money
transmissions. You will not see that the FX margin is included
as a cost. It's not listed as a fee, it's not listed as
anything to the consumer other than, "This is the
FX rate that you're getting." And it could be anywhere up to 6,
7 or 8% on more exotic currency routes, and that is the
evil that this bill will help resolve.
Thank you.
We've got Melissa Lee, Andy Foster.
We'll see how far through we get.
Mine's really quick.
Let's find a group.
Yeah, mine's really quick. Hey, thank you.
What percentage of that hidden fee includes is actually
for, for example, in places like Philippines and other parts of the world
where bank-to-bank transfer isn't actually easy, is the
cash pickup service that they provide?
So Wise doesn't operate any cash business.
But based on our understanding of the market,
there will be a differential FX rate for cash pickup, or there could be a
fixed fee for cash pickup. But that's not really what we work in.
We work in bank-to-bank transfers.
You're right, though, to say that there is a very big cash economy here in terms of
remittances.
This bill would still help those people who make cash remittances because there
is still a hidden FX component of, let's
say, bank-to-cash transfers overseas.
Yep. Thanks.
Andy Foster, we'll try and get through the last two or three.
Sure. Just very quickly. You said that you save
1.9 billion in fees
in 2025,
roughly 120 billion in transactions, so roughly 1.5%
saved. And then later in your submission, you talk about
a 4 to 6% increase in the cost of imports.
I presume that's the entire transaction.
Just trying to get a bit of a feel for what proportion of
the cost of the transaction you see as being
savable
through this, because it looks as like it's about half to a third.
So the proportion, it depends obviously on the amount that is being charged as
hidden fees by a bank or an international money transfer provider.
We don't really have clear ideas on that because the market is not a centralized
market. So a lot of the figures that we're
providing you, we used Edgar, Dunn & Co., which is an
econometrics firm in London.
We would say, though, that the figures that we've got have
a strong academic basis to them. But I do have to confess that there
is a lot about this market we simply do not know, simply because
people are making FX transactions all the time,
and there's no-
Yeah, so sorry. From your perspective, if you reckon saving 1.9
billion, what sort of proportion of the cost that
you apply to consumers who are using that service
would that 1.9 be?
Pounds.
Well, I could just give you the comparison-
Pounds
... would probably be-- Pardon me?
That's okay. Sorry. Melissa's just said pounds. Yeah.
Okay.
But the issue I'm after is proportion.
Yeah. So look, the best way I could probably answer that is to say that the
average FX margin that a bank would charge is about potentially between
2.5 to 4.5%.
We charge 50 basis points on average across about, I think, 7,000
currency pairs. So the proportion that we could potentially save is
somewhere between... Again, it depends on the route, and it depends on
the FX rate that's being offered by a particular bank.
But it could be anywhere up to 80% of the amount that
would cost you would be saved depending on the
route.
That's very helpful. Thank you.
And really quickly, if we can, if someone's
charging a higher marginal rate, isn't that just the cost
of doing business? Like if I go to the supermarket, I don't know how much profit
they've built into their product.
Why would we
legislate that they have to tell you their profit margin when other
companies don't?
We're not asking that you legislate telling people your profit margin.
We're legislating that you tell people what the cost to consumers would be.
So you're right, we don't ask people to give us the
profit margin on a liter of milk, but when we're contemplating what it is that
consumers are getting,
I would say that they're actually getting less milk.
So what you're actually legislating for is to let people know when they go into the
supermarket that a liter of milk is actually a liter of milk.
Okay. Thank you.
Right. Thank you for your time, and a little bit of extra time.
Thank you very much.
We are going to go to Jacob
Pat, who I believe is joining us online as well.
Yeah, so welcome. Jacob, if you can turn on your camera and unmute-
Yeah. I did
... the next five minutes are yours.
If you want to leave some time for questions, that's up to you.
Okay, cool. Kia ora,
and welcome.
I had a chance to read this bill.
I got few points I would like to express.
First of all, I do support the bill
because this bill improves the transparency.
It will make easier to compare the
providers for people like us.
It also encourages the competition between the providers.
It help families to keep
more in their hand
who earns money.
This
bill supports the migrants,
refugees,
and Pacific communities who regularly send money to
overseas.
This will help the
people, the business, who is making a
big profit from
these people who are sending money.
So,
this also
remove the monopoly of some of the companies
in New Zealand.
When we look around the world, there are so many cities,
they have so many companies. For example, in London
or in Sydney or Singapore, you can go anywhere
and exchange
our money for very competitive price.
So, for me,
I'm
having hard-earned money, I don't want to give to a middleman
who is sitting there and doing nothing, pretty much nothing.
So, for me, if I am sending my money from here to
overseas, I want it to go pretty much
full.
So, I always look for the cheap
rate who is giving a best
offer for my New Zealand dollar.
So,
what I see in few years, the cost of living is too high,
so I don't want to spend extra dollar
to someone who is
sitting there as a middleman.
So,
yeah. Pretty much, that's it.
Thank you. And I think we have a question from Marilyn, was it?
Thank you. Yeah.
From you, Celine. Yeah.
Thank you for your submission. I wanted to ask you as a consumer-
Mm-hmm
... in comparing prices when you go to do your
transaction-
Mm-hmm
... what's the information that you want to receive upfront to help you make
an informed choice, to be very clear?
Okay. Well, last month, no, two months before, I
went to Japan. So I want to transfer some New Zealand dollar
into Japanese yen.
I went to the bank. I check on
the online what's the rate in Google.
So I went to the bank, different banks, to be honest, Westpac and ASB
and BNZ, which I got the account with. So they are really high.
Then I went to Travel
New Zealand, that's a exchange company, which is really high, too.
So eventually I end up with
Progressio Change, that is in
Custom Street. So I need to go to
different places, example, Lotus and so many places,
to check the exchange rate,
to
give me a good rate for my New Zealand dollar.
And some of them, when we say,
"According to the Google, today's rate is
blah, blah, blah," but they are saying, "Okay, this is our rate."
Then, yeah. So they are not disclosing too much, you
know what I mean?
So basically, they are sitting there.
If you want to buy Japanese yen, you
give the money and take it or better off.
That's a
simple way, I would say.
So,
what I was saying is that look at Melbourne or
Sydney or
London or anywhere in the world, and you
make it like that. So
the people, for example, the
refugees or migrants or Pacific communities or anyone,
those who are not getting a big bulk of money every week.
They are getting very less money. They want to
save some money to run the family here in New Zealand, as well as
they want to transfer the money to their home country to look
after their people there as well. So-
Thank you
... they are stretching the whole money. It's really hard.
It's really hard
Thank you. We are out of time there, but we appreciate your submission,
Jacob. We are going to move
to Retail NZ.
Yes.
And-
Morena. I'm Karen Young, chief executive of Retail NZ.
I'm joined today by my colleague-
Nicole Deese. I'm the advocacy manager at Retail NZ
I will take our submissions read, and you'll see that we
support the submission. I think a couple of things we'd start off by saying
is that
there's 29,505 retailers across New Zealand, and over
25,000 of those are small to medium-sized retailers.
And what we all know in New Zealand is that we're made up of SMEs,
and SMEs don't have that buying power that some of the
larger players do, which is one of the reasons why we wanted to come
in and talk to you because we feel that we
know that without that level of transparency, then
businesses aren't getting the right information, just as consumers aren't getting
the right information when they are transacting with overseas parties in
terms of buying product to come to New Zealand, and they're
having to do FX exchange rates. Larger businesses obviously
manage their FX in a much more complex and
holistic sort of space. So much as what the
Peanut Butter Collective said and what Wise said, we support the areas that
they talked about.
And I think we also believe that we could go
a little bit further than what's outlined.
And
I think to the question you had earlier, Andy, when you sort of...
And I think
both,
Minister Riley had said the same thing as well, thinking about competition, and
doesn't that just level the playing field?
But I think the whole piece is that at the moment, you actually don't know what the
fees are that you're paying. You don't know what's hidden.
You can go in and look at what a spot price is, and there should be, obviously
there's always going to be a margin either side of that.
But understanding what that margin is in totality is what's
really important for individuals to be able to do.
If we think about the electricity sector, there's been some work done to
ensure that electricity statements for consumers are all very
consistent, so consumers can compare from one to the other.
You think about those sorts of things, we could put in place some standards that
apply across. And
much like the example about the liter of milk,
small businesses and consumers would then
know what they're actually getting for their money and how much of it
is going into fees versus what, you know, compared to third
party. Because until you actually do that transaction, and if you shop
around every week, you won't actually know what that's worth.
So I think they're probably some of the key things.
Yeah. And it is just around
ensuring that it's consistent and fit for everyone, no matter whether it's
their first time owning a business and going to make some of these
international transactions, as it is for a business
owner who's actually been trading internationally for years and years and
years. There's that, I think the term is sufficient information, and
what's sufficient information for one person might not be for another.
So that's why we're recommending that it be drawn up in the legislation
exactly what must be displayed and how.
And we know from our members that anything in the payment space, no matter
when you're dealing with a bank or a credit card company, it's incredibly complex,
and small business owners aren't familiar with that, even if they've been trading
for a long time. They assume that they're getting a good deal,
but it's not necessarily the case.
Okay. Arana William.
I want to ask you about a case that I saw of a small business owner who was
transacting in Australian dollars a lot and found that he
started using a transfer product. I think for him it was Wise.
And he ended up saving thousands of dollars a year on that
transaction. The question I have is, we're not talking about big businesses here
because you're right, they have a relationship with an institutional side of a bank
that will be giving them very close to the RBNZ FX rate.
But for your members who, this required him to basically become
finance expert, to become an expert in his banking services.
But he was also using a merchant service, so the transfers
from customer to him, then
different parts of his business lending and the bank wanted to wrap that all
in for him.
How do small business owners who are also transacting in another
foreign currency get the right kind of information?
I mean, are they coming to you? How are they making sure that
they're getting the best deal, or do we just see that size of half
a billion dollars of drag just on the business owners in New Zealand
for foreign FX as something that's kind of lost to us?
Can we improve this in other ways alongside a regulatory change?
Yeah, look, I think,
we know that SMEs often rely on information coming from a
financial party. So,
either from their bank or who they've normally gone to or, if it's
in a payment space, they rely on terminal providers, all sorts of people that they
assume know best in what they are doing.
And there is always the assumption that something like a bank, which is a
large institutional organization, will be upfront and really clear
about that. And I think the case that was discussed just a little bit earlier where
someone says they've got zero fees, there's never a zero fee, right?
Mm-hmm.
There's al- you know, no one's doing something for nothing.
So actually disclosing, maybe that you're not charging this part, but
actually underneath that there's a fee.
So,
being able to be really clear and then we can go out on behalf of the sector to
make sure that we do a wide range of
comms and engagement to ensure that retailers understand
what they should be seeing and how they should look at those sorts of
transactions. And often for a SME business, their
FX transactions are very ad hoc and in the moment, they're not
necessarily, they can't have forward cover and all those sorts of things that the
larger guys do.
Mm-hmm.
Okay, and last couple of minutes, we've got Limone Lydia.
Thank you. Just really quickly, and probably more of a sub to Arana's question,
would the benefits, how would the benefits be for your cons- customers,
Retail New Zealand, to have that disclosure early, and how important
is it-
That they would understand that and be able to just display it in a
readable-
Mm
... for their businesses so that the information is up front, it's very clear,
understanding your obligation, and what that transaction
would be.
Yeah. Look, I think it's the same benefit for a consumer, basically,
is that you're really fully aware of the information before you're making that
transaction. But in a business situation, it's often about where
the margin sits for their products, and are they passing on those costs?
Are they having to increase prices because of what they're seeing?
So it means that it can be transparent all the way through, and they can then
determine if their price point of what they're selling their products at is the
correct and appropriate price, and therefore hopefully consumers will get a
better outcome because the prices will reflect that.
And on that as well, just in terms of where they choose to source the products
from. If they're trying to decide whether to
source products from locally within New Zealand or internationally from an
international partner, understanding exactly how much those
fees and all those hidden costs might be in terms of that
transaction will mean that they're able to make that more informed
decision as well.
Thank you.
Yeah, okay.
Thank you very much for your submission. You can stay where you are.
We're just going to take a minute to pivot advisors, and we're going to
move to the Better Regional Boundaries Bill.
Very efficient.
We're very efficient with the crossover.
Great.
So,
Better Regional Boundaries Bill,
and well, first submission is from Retail NZ. Welcome, Carolyn and Denise.
Hello.
Well, we're still the same people, so it's really great to see you again, and thank
you for your time. Retail New Zealand
looks after
29,000 plus retail businesses across New Zealand and
230,000 people working in New Zealand.
We largely support this bill. I'm going to get
Denise to lead the conversation in terms of this space.
Yeah. We're very supportive of the intent.
We understand that simplicity in the space of
exactly where boundaries lie and, in terms of those
regions or
cities and towns that are
near boundaries and sometimes cross over in terms of the different
services and Crown agencies that
they
interact with in any given space.
Our main concern is just around the
implementation. It's great that there's a five-year
implementation period,
and there is that opportunity for everyone to get together
under the guidance of the public service commissioner to
decide on where these boundaries should lie.
We're just concerned that without
greater clarity around
leadership in this area, which is why we're calling for an independent
working group to lead that work,
time frames may not be adhered to in terms of being able to make
that five-year time frame, but also
ensuring that everything is considered evenly and
weighted when deciding where these boundaries should be officially
drawn and
adhered to from that public service perspective. Yeah.
And from, I guess, from a country the size of New Zealand, it does make sense if
there is some consistency and real clarity on those boundaries.
And obviously, we're all quite parochial, and we
have an association with our areas.
But in terms of then being able to engage with government
agencies, health areas, police, all of those sorts of
things, it makes sense to have consistency across the country.
Okay. Andy Foster.
Yeah, look, thank you for the submission.
My concern about this is that you've got
some suggestions here that it would be nice to have.
We agree that hubs will be of great benefit in our smaller towns.
Now, I look at some of the government agencies, and I think of
MSD from memory has got five districts across the country.
FIN has got four. I think police have got 13 or 14 or something like
that.
Mm.
They're certainly not down that level of
Otaki, for example.
Yes.
You would not have a
regional or whatever it is, or a local whatever it is.
Mm.
You'd have a police station there. Yeah, sure.
Yeah.
But my question-
But they are within a district, right?
Yeah.
And it's about getting alignment around what do those districts mean.
So my question really is,
which you haven't really touched on, is the potential cost, which we've been
told is possibly significant.
Mm.
But nobody's done any work on it because the bill's just been pulled out of a hat.
Yeah.
And out of turn.
Is what that cost might look like to essentially rearrange pretty well every
government agency in the country.
Do you have any view on that?
We wouldn't have an idea about what the cost, but if it's significant,
that would be a consideration for government to look at.
But I guess,
there could be a...
I think if you look at the whole piece, if the cost is
outrageous, then maybe you look at, okay, what would make sense around
critical services? So are all emergency
services, for example, in the same districts, and those boundaries drawn, and
that would make it much easier for
emergency services and those. So thinking, you start with the whole
piece across everything, and then if that's unworkable, then
what are the pieces that you could do that would still make
improvements into the boundaries that we
currently have?
I guess I'm coming from the perspective that each of these agencies has organized
themselves in a particular way for a particular set of reasons that would then be
questioned and-
Or they may just be historical.
Well, possibly. Possibly. But,
they may not be, but I think we need to understand that. At the moment we don't.
For sure. Yeah, exactly. Why are there boundaries the way they are?
And, in
some ways, if you've got five areas for-
What did you say? It was four MSD-
Oh, I think MSD
... and four for FENZ, and 13 for the police.
It's probably easier to expand out into more rather than contract
people into less. So just doing that work and understanding what that would be.
But it would certainly streamline, the size of the country, for
everyone to be aware of where their boundaries are for their area,
rather than, "Oh, for this I'm in this area, and for that I'm in another area."
Thank you. Can I just ask
about your actual submission? So fundamentally, you see the need for this?
I think that we see some
confusion sometimes in terms of how businesses
operate and where
they may be drawing from emergency services, for
example, or even setting rates and things like that, or how rates are
set and things like that, rubbish collection, those sorts of things.
And I feel like
simplicity, consistency is always a good thing from a
business perspective.
However, we don't necessarily
have a view on
how pressing this issue
is compared to maybe
some other things that the government might be considering.
But, we definitely see that this would have benefits for
the country as a whole, but also in retail and business.
And if you think about some of the...
Sorry to interrupt, but if you think about some of the, we've had a number of state
of emergencies across the country this year.
And at the heart of a lot of that is often
supermarkets, and supermarkets rely on freight transportation
to get product onto shelves so that
consumers can still have food for their cupboards.
And we also know that supermarkets has operated as sort of mini
banks at times of state of emergency, where they're the only place in town we can
get cash out. And one of the things that supermarkets are trying to work out
is how they can streamline their engagement with emergency
services, NZTA, to be able to get access to those
sorts of places. And if there was greater alignment
across services for those areas, that would mean it would be better
benefits to communities.
Thank you. And your point about, or Denise's point about
you'd like to see a more formalized group that looks at the
implementation rather than let the public service commissioner
coordinate with the agencies.
Yeah. I think that's just around making sure that everything
is considered evenly when deciding where to draw these
boundaries, and whether that is financial considerations in terms of some
of the service providers and Crown agencies, or
whether it's in terms of even just geography, location and things
like that, and where our main towns and cities are.
All of that, I think
rather than just having those with the loudest voices or with the
more resources to be able to plead their case,
I think it is important that there is a group of people who
is able to-
Sort of independently-
Independently
... apply some thought
Yeah. Consider all of this. And take some of that weight
off the commissioner as a sole kind of overseer.
Of course, with their guidance. But
we think there would be a lot of benefit for creating that kind of working group.
Okay. Well, thank you very much for your time this morning on both calls.
We appreciate it.
Thank you.
Enjoy the rest of your day. We've got one more via Zoom or maybe
phone.
The Family Estate of Hereditary Chiefs.
Just give them a minute to come online.
Someone's getting the phone here.
Thank
you.
Are they online?
They're just trying to ring the phone, but it's not on. Yeah.
Okay. We'll give it a minute to see if he can connect in.
Fine.
Mm.
And if that happens.
Mm-hmm.
Hope it happens.
Everyone does the...
Hi. Sorry. I'm unable to take your call.
Okay.
Call back.
So we will, uh-
At the tone, record your message
Okay. We will move on and leave that one.
We are going to just move to item...
Oh, we don't have any advisors here.
Are there advisors